<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//Boost//DTD BoostBook XML V1.0//EN"
  "http://www.boost.org/tools/boostbook/dtd/boostbook.dtd">

<?psgml nofill screen programlisting literallayout?>

<chapter id="bbv2.tutorial" status="draft">
  <title>Tutorial</title>

  <section id="bbv2.tutorial.hello">
    <title>Hello, world</title>

    <para>The simplest project that Boost.Build can construct is
      stored in <filename>example/hello/</filename> directory. The
      project is described by a file
      called <filename>Jamfile</filename> that contains:

<programlisting>
exe hello : hello.cpp ;
</programlisting>

      Even with this simple setup, you can do some interesting
      things. First of all, just invoking <command>bjam</command> will
      build the debug variant of the <command>hello</command>
      executable by compiling and
      linking <filename>hello.cpp</filename>.  Now, to build the
      release variant of <command>hello</command>, invoke

<screen>
bjam release
</screen>

      Note that debug and release variants are created in different
      directories, so you can switch between variants or even build
      multiple variants at once, without any unneccessary
      recompilation. Let's extend the example by adding another line
      to our project's <filename>Jamfile</filename>:

<programlisting>
exe hello2 : hello.cpp ;
</programlisting>

      Now we can build both the debug and release variants of our
      project:

<screen>
bjam debug release
</screen>

      Note that two variants of <command>hello2</command> are linked.
      Since we have already built both variants
      of <command>hello</command>, hello.cpp won't be recompiled;
      instead the existing object files will just be linked into the
      corresponding variants of <command>hello2</command>. Now 
      let's remove all the built products:

<screen>
bjam --clean debug release
</screen>

      It's also possible to build or clean specific targets.  The
      following two commands, respectively, build or clean only the
      debug version of <command>hello2</command>.

<screen>
bjam hello2
bjam --clean hello2
</screen>
    </para>

  </section>
  <section id="bbv2.tutorial.properties">
    <title>Properties</title>

    <para>
      To portably represent aspects of target configuration such as
      debug and release variants, or single- and multi-threaded
      builds, Boost.Build uses <firstterm>features</firstterm> with
      associated <firstterm>values</firstterm>.  For
      example, the "debug-symbols" feature can have a value of "on" or
      "off".  A <firstterm>property</firstterm> is just a (feature,
      value) pair.  When a user initiates a build, Boost.Build
      automatically translates the requested properties into appropriate
      command-line flags for invoking toolset components like compilers
      and linkers.</para>

    <para>There are many built-in features that can be combined to
      produce arbitrary build configurations.  The following command
      builds the project's &quot;release&quot; variant with inlining
      disabled and debug symbols enabled:

<screen>
bjam release inlining=off debug-symbols=on
</screen>
</para>

    <para>Properties on the command-line are specified with the syntax:

<screen>
<replaceable>feature-name</replaceable>=<replaceable>feature-value</replaceable>
</screen>
</para>

    <para>The "release" and "debug" that we've seen
      in <command>bjam</command> invocations are just a shorthand way to
      specify values of the "variant" feature.  For example, the command
      above could also have been written this way:

      <screen>
bjam variant=release inlining=off debug-symbols=on
      </screen>
    </para>

    <para>  &quot;variant&quot; is so commonly-used that it has been given
      special status as an <firstterm>implicit</firstterm> feature
      &#x2014; Boost.Build will deduce the its identity just from the name
      of one of its values.  
    </para>

    <para>
      A complete description of features can be found
      <link linkend="bbv2.reference.features">here</link>. 
    </para>


    <section id="bbv2.tutorial.properties.requirements">
      <title>Build Requests and Target Requirements</title>

      <para>      
        The set of properties specified in the command line constitute a
        <firstterm>build request</firstterm> &#x2014; a description of
        the desired properties for building the requested targets (or,
        if no targets were explicitly requested, the project in the
        current directory).  The <emphasis>actual</emphasis> properties
        used for building targets is typically a combination of the
        build request and properties derived from the
        project's <filename>Jamfile</filename>s.  For example, the
        locations of <code>#include</code>d header files are normally
        not specified on the command-line, but described
        in <filename>Jamfile</filename>s as <firstterm>target
          requirements</firstterm> and automatically combined with the
        build request for those targets.  Multithread-enabled
        compilation is another example of a typical target requirement.
        The <filename>Jamfile</filename> fragment below illustrates how
        these requirements might be specified.
      </para>

<programlisting>
exe hello 
    : hello.cpp
    : &lt;include&gt;/home/ghost/Work/boost &lt;threading&gt;multi
    ;
</programlisting>

      <para> 
        When <filename>hello</filename> is built, the two
        requirements specified above will normally always be present.
        If the build request given on the <command>bjam</command>
        command-line explictly contradicts a target's requirements,
        the command-line usually overrides (or, in the case of
        &quot;free&quot; feautures like <code>&lt;include&gt;</code>
        <footnote>See <xref
        linkend="bbv2.reference.features.attributes"/></footnote>,
        augments) the target requirements.  However, when a
        contradiction of a target's requrements involves certain
        <firstterm>link-incompatible</firstterm> features, the target
        will be skipped.  See <xref linkend=
        "bbv2.reference.variants.compat"/> for more information.
      </para>

    </section>
    <section id="bbv2.tutorial.properties.project_attributes">
      <title>Project Attributes</title>

      <para>
        If we want the same requirements for our other
        target, <filename>hello2</filename>, we could simply duplicate
        them.  However, as projects grow, that approach leads to a great
        deal of repeated boilerplate in Jamfiles.
        
        Fortunately, there's a better way. Each project (i.e. each
        <filename>Jamfile</filename>), can specify a set of <firstterm>attributes</firstterm>,
        including requirements:

<programlisting>
project 
    : requirements &lt;include&gt;/home/ghost/Work/boost &lt;threading&gt;multi 
    ;

exe hello : hello.cpp ;
exe hello2 : hello.cpp ;
</programlisting>

        The effect would be as if we specified the same requirement for
        both <command>hello</command> and <command>hello2</command>.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="bbv2.tutorial.hierarchy">
    <title>Project Hierarchies</title>

    <para>So far we've only considered examples with one project
      (i.e. with one <filename>Jamfile</filename>). A typical large
      software project would be composed of sub-projects organized
      into a tree. The top of the tree is called the
      <firstterm>project root</firstterm>.  Besides a
      <filename>Jamfile</filename>, the project root directory
      contains a file called <filename>project-root.jam</filename>. Every other
      <filename>Jamfile</filename> in the project has a single parent
      project, rooted in the nearest parent directory containing a
      <filename>Jamfile</filename>. For example, in the following
      directory layout:

<screen>
top/ 
  |
  +-- Jamfile
  +-- project-root.jam
  |
  +-- src/
  |    |
  |    +-- Jamfile
  |    `-- app.cpp
  | 
  `-- util/
       |
       +-- foo/
       .    |
       .    +-- Jamfile
       .    `-- bar.cpp
</screen>

      <!-- "lib/lib1/lib1" changed to "util/foo/bar" to avoid confusion -->

      the project root is <filename>top/</filename>.  Because there is
      no <filename>Jamfile</filename> in
      <filename>top/util/</filename>, the projects in
      <filename>top/src/</filename> and
      <filename>top/util/foo/</filename> are immediate children of the
      root project.
    </para>

    <para>
      Projects inherit all attributes (such as requirements)
      from their parents.  Inherited requirements are combined with
      any requirements specified by the sub-project.  
      For example, if <filename>top/Jamfile</filename> has

<programlisting>
&lt;include&gt;/home/ghost/local
</programlisting>

      in its requirements, then all of its sub-projects will have it
      in their requirements, too.  Of course, any project can add
      additional includes. <footnote>Many features will be overridden,
      rather than added-to, in sub-projects.  See <xref
      linkend="bbv2.reference.features.attributes"/> for more
      information</footnote> More details can be found in the section
      on <link linkend= "bbv2.advanced.projects">projects</link>.
    </para>

    <para>
      Invoking <command>bjam</command> without explicitly specifying
      any targets on the command-line builds the project rooted in the
      current directory.  Building a project does not automatically
      cause its sub-projects to be built unless the parent project's
      <filename>Jamfile</filename> explicitly requests it. In our
      example, <filename>top/Jamfile</filename> might contain:

<programlisting>
build-project src ;
</programlisting>

      which would cause the project in <filename>top/src/</filename>
      to be built whenever the project in <filename>top/</filename> is
      built. However, targets in <filename>top/util/foo/</filename>
      will be built only if they are needed by targets in
      <filename>top/</filename> or <filename>top/src/</filename>.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="bbv2.tutorial.libs">
    <title>Libraries and Dependent Targets</title>

    <comment>TODO: need to make this
      section consistent with "examples-v2/libraries".</comment>

    <para>
      Targets that are "needed" by other targets are called
      <firstterm>dependencies</firstterm> of those other targets.  The
      targets that need the other targets are called
      <firstterm>dependent</firstterm> targets.
    </para>

    <para>To get a feeling of target dependencies, let's continue the
      above example and see how <filename>src/Jamfile</filename> can
      use libraries from <filename>util/foo</filename>.  Assume
      util/foo/Jamfile contains:

<programlisting>
lib bar : bar.cpp ;
</programlisting>

      Then, to use this library in <filename>src/Jamfile</filename>, we can write:

<programlisting>
exe app : app.cpp ../util/foo//bar ;
</programlisting>

      While <code>app.cpp</code> refers to a regular source file,
      <code>../util/foo//bar</code> is a reference to another target:
      a library "bar" declared in the <filename>Jamfile</filename> at
      <filename>../util/foo</filename>.  When linking the
      <command>app</command> executable, the appropriate version of
      <code>bar</code> will be built and linked in. What do we mean by
      "appropriate"? For example, suppose we build "app" with:

<screen>
bjam app optimization=full cxxflags=-w-8080
</screen>

      Which properties must be used to build <code>foo</code>? The
      answer is that some properties are
      <firstterm>propagated</firstterm> &#x2014; Boost.Build attempts to
      use dependencies with the same value of propagated features. The
      &lt;optimization&gt; feature is propagated, so both "app" and
      "foo" will be compiled with full optimization. But
      &lt;cxxflags&gt; feature is not propagated: its value will be
      added as-is to compiler flags for "a.cpp", but won't affect
      "foo". There is still a couple of problems. First, the library
      probably has some headers which must be used when compiling
      "app.cpp". We could use requirements on "app" to add those
      includes, but then this work will be repeated for all programs
      which use "foo". A better solution is to modify
      util/foo/Jamfilie in this way:

<programlisting>
project 
    : usage-requirements &lt;include&gt;.
    ;

lib foo : foo.cpp ;
</programlisting>

      Usage requirements are requirements which are applied to
      dependents. In this case, &lt;include&gt; will be applied to all
      targets which use "foo" &#x2014; i.e. targets which have "foo"
      either in sources or in dependency properties. You'd need to
      specify usage requirements only once, and programs which use "foo"
      don't have to care about include paths any longer. Or course, the
      path will be interpreted relatively to "util/foo" and will be
      adjusted according to the <command>bjam</command>s invocation
      directory. For
      example, if building from project root, the final compiler's
      command line will contain <option>-Ilib/foo</option>.
    </para>

    <para>The second problem is that we hardcode the path to library's
      Jamfile. Imagine it's hardcoded in 20 different places and we
      change the directory layout. The solution is to use project ids
      &#x2014; symbolic names, not tied to directory layout. First, we
      assign a project id to Jamfile in util/foo:</para>

<programlisting>
project foo
    : usage-requirements &lt;include&gt;.
    ;
</programlisting>

    <para>
      Second, we use the project id to refer to the library in
      src/Jamfile:

<programlisting>
exe app : app.cpp /foo//bar ;
</programlisting>

      The "/foo//bar" syntax is used to refer to target "foo" in
      project with global id "/foo" (the slash is used to specify global
      id). This way, users of "foo" do not depend on its location, only
      on id, which is supposedly stable. The only thing left, it to make
      sure that src/Jamfile knows the project id that it uses. We add to
      top/Jamfile the following line:

<programlisting>
use-project /foo : util/foo ;
</programlisting>

      Now, all projects can refer to "foo" using the symbolic
      name. If the library is moved somewhere, only a single line in the
      top-level Jamfile should be changed.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="bbv2.tutorial.depends">
    <title>Library dependencies</title>

    <para>The previous example was simple. Often, there are long chains
      of dependencies between libraries. The main application is a thin
      wrapper on top of library with core logic, which uses library of
      utility functions, which uses boost filesystem library.
      Expressing these dependencies is straightforward:</para>

<programlisting>
lib utils : utils.cpp /boost/filesystem//fs ;   
lib core : core.cpp utils ;
exe app : app.cpp core ;
</programlisting>

    <para>So, what's the reason to even mention this case? First,
      because it's a bit more complex that it seems. When using shared
      linking, libraries are build just as written, and everything will
      work. However, what happens with static linking? It's not
      possible to include another library in static library.
      Boost.Build solves this problem by returning back library targets
      which appear as sources for static libraries. In this case, if
      everything is built statically, the "app" target will link not
      only "core" library, but also "utils" and
      "/boost/filesystem//fs".</para>

    <para>So, the net result is that the above code will work for both
      static linking and for shared linking.</para>

    <para>Sometimes, you want all applications in some project to link
      to a certain library. Putting the library in sources of all
      targets is possible, but verbose. You can do better by using the
      &lt;source&gt; property. For example, if "/boost/filesystem//fs"
      should be linked to all applications in your project, you can add
      &lt;source&gt;/boost/filesystem//fs to requirements of the
      project, like this:</para>

<programlisting>
project 
   : requirements &lt;source&gt;/boost/filesystem//fs
   ;   
</programlisting>
    </section>

  <section id="bbv2.tutorial.linkage">
    <title>Static and shared libaries</title>

    <para>While the
      previous section explained how to create and use libraries, it
      omitted one important detail. Libraries can be either
      <emphasis>static</emphasis>, which means they are included in executable
      files which use them, or <emphasis>shared</emphasis> (a.k.a.
      <emphasis>dynamic</emphasis>), which are only referred to from executables,
      and must be available at run time. Boost.Build can work with both
      types. By default, all libraries are shared. This is much more
      efficient in build time and space. But the need to install all
      libraries to some location is not always convenient, especially
      for debug builds. Also, if the installed shared library changes,
      all application which use it might start to behave differently.
    </para>

    <para>Static libraries do not suffer from these problems, but
      considerably increase the size of application. Before describing
      static libraries, it's reasonable to give another, quite simple
      approach. If your project is built with
      &lt;hardcode-dll-paths&gt;true property, then the application
      will include the full paths for all shared libraries, eliminating
      the above problems. Unfortunately, you no longer can move shared
      library to a different location, which makes this option suitable
      only for debug builds. Further, only gcc compiler supports this
      option.</para>

    <para>Building a library statically is easy. You'd need to change
      the value of &lt;link&gt; feature from it's deafault value
      <literal>shared</literal>, to <literal>static</literal>. So, to build everything as
      static libraries, you'd say</para>

<screen>
bjam link=static
</screen>

    <para>
      on the command line. The linking mode can be fine-tuned on
      per-target basis.

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Suppose your library can be only build statically. This is
            easily achieved using requirements:

<programlisting>
lib l : l.cpp : &lt;link&gt;static ;
</programlisting>
            
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            What if library can be both static and shared, but when
            using it in specific executable, you want it static?
            <link linkend="bbv2.advanced.targets.references">Target
              references</link> are here to help:

<programlisting>
exe important : main.cpp helpers/&lt;link&gt;static ;
</programlisting>

          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            What if the library is defined in some other project, which
            you cannot change. But still, you want static linking to that
            library in all cases. You can use target references everywhere:

<programlisting>
exe e1 : e1.cpp /other_project//bar/&lt;link&gt;static ;
exe e10 : e10.cpp /other_project//bar/&lt;link&gt;static ;
</programlisting>

            but that's far from being convenient. Another way is to
            introduce a level of indirection: create a local target, which will
            refer to static version of <filename>foo</filename>. Here's the
            solution:

<programlisting>
alias foo : /other_project//bar/&lt;link&gt;static ;
exe e1 : e1.cpp foo ;
exe e10 : e10.cpp foo ;
</programlisting>

            Note that the <link linkend="bbv2.builtins.alias">alias</link> 
            rule is specifically used for rename a reference to a target and possibly
            change the properties.

          </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="bbv2.tutorial.conditions">
    <title>Conditions and alternatives</title>

    <para>As we've just figured out, properties can significally affect the
      way targets are built. The processing of the &lt;link&gt; feature is
      built in the build system, and is quite complex. But there is a couple
      of mechanisms which allow ordinary users to do different things 
      depending on properties.
    </para>

    <para>The first mechanism is called <firstterm>conditinal
        requirement</firstterm>. For example, you might want to set specific
      defines when the library is build as shared, or you have your own define
      to be used in release mode. Here's a piece of Jamfile.
<programlisting>
lib network : network.cpp 
    : &lt;link&gt;shared:&lt;define&gt;NEWORK_LIB_SHARED 
      &lt;variant&gt;release:&lt;define&gt;EXTRA_FAST
    ;
</programlisting>
      This will have exactly the effect we wanted: whenever &lt;link&gt;shared
      is in properties, &lt;define&gt;NEWORK_LIB_SHARED will be in properties
      as well.
    </para>

    <para>
      Sometimes different variant of a target are so different, that
      describing them using conditional requirements would be hard. Imagine
      that a library has different sources on two supported toolsets, and
      dummy implementation for all the other toolset. We can express this
      situation using <firstterm>target alternatives</firstterm>:
<programlisting>
lib demangler : dummy_demangler.cpp ;
lib demangler : demangler_gcc.cpp : &lt;toolset&gt;gcc ;
lib demangler : demangler_msvc.cpp : &lt;toolset&gt;msvc ;
</programlisting>
      The proper alternative will be automatically selected. 
    </para>
    
  </section>


  <section id="bbv2.tutorial.prebuilt">
    <title>Prebuilt targets</title>

    <para>
      We've just learned how to use libraries which are created by
      Boost.Build. But some libraries are not. At the same time, those
      libraries can have different versions (release and debug, for
      example), that we
      should select depending on build properties. Prebuilt targets
      provide a mechanism for that. Jamfile in util/lib2 can contain:

<programlisting>
lib lib2
    : 
    : &lt;file&gt;lib2_release.a &lt;variant&gt;release
    ;

lib lib2
    : 
    : &lt;file&gt;lib2_debug.a &lt;variant&gt;debug
    ;
</programlisting>

      This defines two alternatives for target "lib2", and for each
      one names a prebuilt file. Naturally, there are no sources.
      Instead, the &lt;file&gt; feature is used to specify the file name.
      Which alternative is selected depends on properties of dependents.
      If "app" binary should use "lib2", we can write:

<programlisting>
exe app : app.cpp ../util/lib2//lib2 ;
</programlisting>

      If we build release version of "app", then it will be linked
      with "lib2_release.a", and debug version will use "lib2_debug.a".
      Another important kind of prebuilt targets are system libraries
      &#x2014; more specifically, libraries which are automatically found
      by the compiler. E.g. gcc uses "-l" switch for that. Such libraries
      should be declared almost like regular ones:

<programlisting>
lib zlib : : &lt;name&gt;z ;
</programlisting>

      We again don't specify any sources, but give a name which
      should be passed to the compiler. In this example, and for gcc
      compiler, the "-lz" option will be added. Paths where library
      should be searched can also be specified:

<programlisting>
lib zlib : : &lt;name&gt;z &lt;search&gt;/opt/lib ;
</programlisting>

      And, of course, two variants can be used:

<programlisting>
lib zlib : : &lt;name&gt;z &lt;variant&gt;release ;
lib zlib : : &lt;name&gt;z_d &lt;variant&gt;debug ;
</programlisting>

      Of course, you'll probably never in your life need debug
      version of zlib, but for other libraries this is quite reasonable.
    </para>

    <para>More advanced use of prebuilt target is described in <ulink
        url="doc/recipes.html#site_config_targets">recipes</ulink>.</para>

  </section>

</chapter>

<!--
     Local Variables:
     mode: xml
     sgml-indent-data:t
     sgml-parent-document:("userman.xml" "chapter")
     sgml-set-face: t
     sgml-omittag:nil
     sgml-shorttag:nil
     sgml-namecase-general:t
     sgml-general-insert-case:lower
     sgml-minimize-attributes:nil
     sgml-always-quote-attributes:t
     sgml-indent-step:2
     sgml-exposed-tags:nil
     sgml-local-catalogs:nil
     sgml-local-ecat-files:nil
     End:
-->
